So what exactly is a wave? A wave is
basically a disturbance that can cause
matter to oscillate up and down or back
and forth with the result of
transporting energy from one place to
another. Now there's two types of waves
that you need to be familiar with.
Transverse waves and longitudinal waves.
So what exactly is a transverse wave?
A good example of a transverse wave is a
wave on a string. Let's say if you apply
a force and you create a wave on a
string.
Notice that the wave is traveling
towards the right that is in the x
direction but the oscillations
the string oscillates up and down in the
y direction.
So as you can see the oscillations are
perpendicular
to the wave motion and that is a feature
of a transverse wave.
In a longitudinal wave,
the oscillations are in the same
direction
as the wave motion. A good example of a
longitudinal wave is a soundwave.
In a soundwave, you have regions of high
and low pressure.
Let me see how I can draw this.
So let's say this shaded region is a
region of high pressure
and then this lightly shaded region is a
region of low pressure.
A sound wave is basically a pressure
wave.
So the pressure oscillates from high to
low.
When the pressure is high, the molecules
in the air are very close together. So
you have a region of high density.
So that's a region of compression.
Where the pressure is low, the molecules
are further apart. And so you have a
region of low density or an expansion
also called a rare action. So a sound
wave is a good example of a longitudinal
wave. So the wave is moving in the x
direction and the oscillations are also
in the x direction.
As it compresss and expands, it's
oscillating in the x direction. So
that's an example of a longitudinal
wave.
Another example of a longitudinal wave
is a wave on a spring.
If you compress and expand a spring, you
can create a longitudinal wave.
So as you can see here we have an area
of compression
and here is an area of expansion.
So the wave is traveling towards the
right
and we have regions of
compression and expansion. So the
oscillations
are in the x direction.
So that's another example of a
longitudinal wave.
Now let's talk about the transverse wave
which looks like a sine wave.
The peak is known as
the crest
and the lowest point of the wave is
called the trough.
The distance between the center and the
peak is known as the amplitude.
And the distance
between successive peaks, let's say from
here to here,
that is known as the wavelength. That's
how long the wave is.
This is one cycle from these two
positions.
So that is one full cycle when the wave
goes up back to the middle and then down
and back to the middle.
So that's one full cycle. Now you need
to be familiar with the words period and
frequency.
The period which is represented by
capital T, it's the time it takes for
the wave to complete one cycle. So you
could find it by taking by dividing the
total time by the total number of cycles
and you'll get the time per single
cycle.
The frequency
is the reciprocal of the period. The
frequency is how many cycles that can
occur in 1 second. So it's the number of
cycles
per unit time
and the frequency is 1 / the period.
The unit for frequency is hertz
or seconds to the minus one.
The unit for wavelength is typically in
meters. The wavelength times the
frequency is equal to the speed. Make
sure you know this equation. You'll need
it whenever you have to solve problems.
So let's focus on the units here. So
wavelength is in meters. Frequency is
sus or 1 /
v is meters/s. That's the speed.
Now there's another equation that you
need to know.
Let's say if you apply a force on a
string, you can produce a wave that will
travel along the spring. And there's an
equation that will help you to calculate
the speed of the wave. And here it is.
The wave speed is equal to the square
root of the tension force that you apply
divided by mu where mu is the mass per
unit length or also known as the linear
density. Mu has the units kilograms per
meter.
So if you don't want to use the letter
U, you can replace it with
M / L,
which if you want to rearrange that
equation, it's the same as the square
root of F
times the length of the spring, I mean
the string divided by the mass.
So, here's a question for you.
If you increase the tension force,
what's going to happen to the wave
speed?
If the force increases, the velocity
will increase.
And it makes sense because the force is
in the numerator of the equation.
Anytime you increase the numerator of a
fraction, the value of the entire
fraction goes up.
Now, if we double the magnitude of the
force,
how will that affect the wave speed?
Will it double, triple, quadruple? All
you got to do is plug in two into the
equation and everything else that's
constant, keep it the same or replace it
with one. So if we replace f with two
that tells us that the velocity will
increase by a factor of the roo of
two. Now what if we increase the force
by a factor of four?
What effect will that have on the speed
or the velocity of the wave?
The square root of four is two. So if
you quadruple the force, the wave speed
will increase by a factor of two.
Now what about the linear density?
If we increase the linear density,
what effect will it have on the wave
speed?
Now because mu is in the bottom of the
equation,
it's inversely related to the speed. So
if you increase the linear density, the
speed decreases. And it makes sense. If
you have more mass per unit length,
there's more inertia. And whenever you
have an object with more mass, it's
harder to move. Heavy objects tend to
move slower. Lighter objects tend to
move faster. So if we increase the mass
per unit length, we should expect that
the wave speed will decrease as long as
the tension force remains constant.
Now if we increase the linear density by
a factor of four, what effect will that
have on the wave speed? So if we replace
mu with four, we have the square root of
1/4. The square root of 1 is 1 and the
square roo of 4 is two. So the
speed is going to be 1/2 its original
value.
So if you increase the tension force by
a factor of four, the speed will double.
If you increase the linear density by a
factor of four, the speed will be 1/2 of
its value. Likewise, if you increase the
tension force by a factor of 9, the
speed will increase by the square root
of 9 or it's going to triple in value.
And if you increase the linear density
by a factor of 9, the speed is going to
be 1/3 of its original value.
Let's work on some problems. A tension
of 1500 newtons is applied to a.5 kg
wire. that is 10 meters long and we're
given the wavelength as well. What is
the speed of the wave? Well, we know
that we could find the speed of the wave
using this equation. It's the square
root of the tension force divided by the
linear density.
So, let's find the linear density first,
which is mass divided by the length of
the wire. The mass is.5 kg
and the wire
is 10 m long.
So.5 / 10
is 0.05
kilogram per meter.
So that's the linear density. Now we can
find the wave speed. The tension force
is 1500
/ 05.
1500 / 05 is 30,000. and the square root
of 30,000
is 173.2.
So this is the speed of the wave on the
string or on the wire.
Now that we have the speed of the wave,
let's calculate the frequency. So what
equation can we use to find the
frequency?
If you recall the velocity is equal to
the wavelength times the frequency.
So the wavelength
is the velocity or the speed divided by
the frequency.
But we have the wavelength. So let's
solve for frequency instead. That's what
I meant to do. So the frequency
is the velocity divided by the
wavelength.
The velocity is 173.2 m/s.
The wavelength is.15 m.
So the unit meters will cancel giving
you the unit one over a second which is
hertz.
So it's going to be 173.2
/ 15 m. So the frequency of this
particular uh wave
is 1154.7
hertz.
Here's another problem that we could
try. The crest of a water wave passes a
boat every 2.5 seconds. The wave crests
are 10 meters apart. What is the period,
frequency, wavelength, and wave speed?
So let's draw a picture. So let's draw a
water wave.
So the distance between wave crests
are 10 m.
That is the wavelength. So that's the
answer to part C.
Now notice that the wave passes the boat
every 2.5 seconds. The time it takes for
a wave to complete one cycle is the
period. So the period is 2.5 seconds.
So that's the answer to part A. Now the
frequency is 1 / the period. So it's 1
over 2.5
which is about
04 hertz.
Now how can we find the wave speed?
There's two ways in which you can find
the wave speed.
So let's make some space. The first
technique that you can use is the wave
speed is equal to the wavelength times
the frequency. So the wavelength is 10.
The frequency is 04. 10 *4 is 4. So it's
4 m/s.
Another equation that you can use is the
wavelength divided by the period.
This is 10 / 2.5 which will also give
you 4 m/s.
So you have two different ways to
calculate the wave speed.
Go ahead and try this problem. What
tension force is required to create a
wave that has a wavelength of 15 cm and
a frequency of 13 hertz using a string
that has a linear density of 75 kg per
meter. So go ahead and take a minute and
work on this problem.
So the equation that we need to find the
tension force
is velocity is equal to the square root
of the force / the linear density.
So let's go ahead and solve for f.
Let's square both sides of the equation.
So v ^2 is equal to f / the linear
density.
So let's multiply both sides by the
linear density and then we can get the
equation for f.
So f is the product of the linear
density time the square of the speed.
Now we don't know what the wave speed
is. So we need another equation to find
it.
The other equation that we can use is
this equation. The wave speed is equal
to the wavelength time the frequency.
The wavelength is 15 cm. We can convert
that to meters by dividing it by 100. 1
meter is 100 cm.
So 15 centimeters divided by 100 is.15
m. Let's multiply it by a frequency of
13 hertz.
So the wave speed
is 15 * 13
and it's about 1.95
m/s.
So now we could take this value and plug
it into this equation. So it's going to
be the linear density which is 75
times the square of the wave speed.
1.95^ squared is about
3.8 and if we multiply that by 75
you should get an answer of 2.85 hertz.
I mean not hertz but newtons.
So that is the tension force that is
required to create a wave with the
following uh characteristics.
How long will it take a wave traveling
from one end of a 85 m long wire to the
other end if a tension force of 300
newtons is applied to the 5 kg wire?
So we need to find the time it takes to
go from one end of the wire to the other
end.
So let's say this is the wire
and this is point A and point B. Now the
wire is 85 m long.
Once you apply a force and once the wave
is created, the wave will continue to
move at constant speed.
The equation that relates distance,
constant speed, and time is this
equation. D is equal to VT.
We have the distance that the wave
travels from one end to the other end.
It's the length of the wire, which is 85
m.
We're looking for the time. So, what
we're missing is the wave speed.
So, we can find the wave speed using
this equation.
But first, let's find the linear
density.
The linear density is the mass divided
by the length. The mass is uh 5 kg
and the wire
is 85 m long.
So if we divide those two numbers,
you should get
0 5 882
kg per meter for the linear density.
Now let's plug it into this formula. So
the speed is going to be the square root
of the tension force which is 300 / the
linear density.
300 / 05882
that's 5100 and the square root of that
number is 71.4.
So V is 71.4. 4 m/s.
So now using the equation d is equal to
vt,
we can now find the time. So the
distance is 85 m. The speed is 71.4 m/s.
And let's solve for t. We can do that by
dividing both sides by 71.4.
So 85 / 71.4
is equal to 1.19.
So, it's going to take 1.19 seconds for
the wave to travel from one end of the
wire to the other end.
Now, let's talk about wave intensity.
The intensity of a wave is defined as
the power emitted by the source divided
by the surface area of a sphere.
You can just put a for area if you want.
The surface area of a sphere is 4 pi r^
2. So intensity is equal to the power /
4 pi r 2. The intensity has the units
watts per square meter.
The unit of power is the watt and the
unit for area is always square meters.
It could be square feet, square yards,
but the standard unit is square meters.
Power is defined as work divided by
time.
And keep in mind work is basically the
change in kinetic energy.
So you can view power as being energy
over time.
Work is in the unit jewels and time is
measured in seconds.
So power is the rate of energy transfer.
One watt means that one jewel of energy
is being transferred every second.
Now since intensity is power / 4i
r^ 2
we can say that the intensity is
proportional to 1 / r^2
where r is the distance between a point
of interest and the source. So let's say
if we have a source, we'll call it S
and 1 meter from the source, the
intensity is measured to be 900 watts
per square meter. What is the intensity
at a distance of 2 m away from the
source?
According to this expression, the
intensity is inversely related to the
square of the radius.
So as the distance increases
the intensity will decrease.
This is known as the inverse square law.
So if we double the value of r, if we
double the distance, what is the effect
on the intensity?
Well, if you plug it into the
expression,
if you replace r for two, since it
doubles, 1 / 2 ^2 is
1/4.
So, the intensity is going to be 1/4 of
its original value. So, that is 1/4 of
900,
which is basically 225.
Now, what is the intensity 3 m away from
the source?
What do you think the answer is?
So if we triple the distance, what
happens to the intensity?
3^2 is 9. So it's going to be 1 over 9
of its original value. 1 9th of 900 is
100.
So it decreases by a factor of 9. So if
we quadruple the distance, if we
increase the distance by a factor of
four, the intensity will decrease by a
factor of the square of four, which is
16.
So it's going to be 1 16 of its original
value.
Now, there's an equation that can help
us to get that answer, but let's talk
about how to derive the equation first.
So we're going to take the ratio of two
intensities. I2 / I1.
Now the intensity we know it's the power
divided by the surface area.
So let's assume that these are the
different intensities for the same
source. So if we have the source S and
if we wish to calculate
the intensity at a larger distance away
from the source,
we can use this equation. So the source
is going to have the same power
represented by P.
However, R is going to change.
I1 is going to be P / 4 R1^ 2.
The only reason why I have a subscript
for R is because R will change in this
equation.
The R value that corresponds to I1 is
different than the R value that
corresponds to I2. However, I don't have
a subscript for P because the the power
of the source remains the same.
So, we can cancel P in the equation and
we can cancel 4 pi.
So this is equal to 1 / r2 2 / 1 / r1^ 2
at which point we can multiply the top
and bottom by r1 2.
In this case these two will cancel.
So therefore we have the equation I2 /
I1 is equal to R1^ 2 / R2 2.
Now in the last example we said that the
intensity was 900
when the distance was 1 meter away from
the source. What is the new intensity if
we triple
the value if we triple the distance to
three. Now, we know the answer is 100,
but let's use the equation to get that
answer.
So, we're looking for I2. I1 is 900.
R1 is 1 2 and R2 is going to be 3.
1 2 is 1. 3 2 is 9. So, I2 / 900 is 1 /
9.
So let's cross multiply. 900 * 1 is 900
and that's equal to 9 * I2. So now we
need to divide both sides by 9. So I2 is
900 / 9 or 100.
So you can use that equation to find the
new intensity at a different distance.
If you have another intensity at a
certain distance,
if you recall from the simple harmonic
motion of springs,
the elastic potential energy is equal to
12 kx^2
where x is the distance or the
displacement
of the spring being stretched or
compressed from its natural length.
Now the maximum displacement is known as
the amplitude.
The mechanical energy which is the total
energy of the system it's 12 k * a^ 2.
So therefore we could say that the total
energy of the system is proportional to
the square of the amplitude.
Now we know that intensity is power /
area
and power you can view it as energy
divided by time.
So notice that E is on top. So we could
say that intensity
is proportional to energy
which is proportional to the square of
the amplitude. So therefore intensity is
proportional to the square of the
amplitude.
So if you increase the amplitude
the intensity will increase.
If you double the amplitude the
intensity will increase by a factor of 4
because 2 ^2 is 4.
Now we know that intensity is inversely
related
to the square of the radius and we have
the equation I2 / I1 is equal to
R1^
2 / R2 2 because it's inversely related
to it. Notice that these subscripts are
flipped. They're opposite of each other.
But the intensity is directly related to
the square of the amplitude. So the
subscripts are going to match. Since we
have I2 on top, we're going to have A2
on top.
So it's going to be the square of A2 /
the square of A1.
So therefore, these two are equal to
each other.
So if we take the square root of both
sides,
we're going to get this expression. A2 /
A1 is equal to R1 / R2.
So this tells us that the distance is
inversely related to the amplitude.
So if we increase the distance by a
factor of two, the amplitude will be 12
of the original value. The amplitude is
inversely related to r, but not to the
square of r.
It's inversely related to r to the first
power. So if we triple the distance, the
amplitude will decrease by a factor of
three. If we quadruple the distance,
it's going to decrease by a factor of
four. If we cut the distance in half,
the amplitude will double.
If we reduce it to a third of its
original value, the amplitude will
triple.
So, make sure you understand that. So,
now let's work on some problems.
Let's start with this problem. A lamp
emits 500 jew of energy every 4 seconds.
What is the rate of energy emitted by
the lamp? The rate at which energy is
transferred is power. And power is
basically the energy divided by time.
Work is equal to the energy that's
transferred.
So it could be work over time or energy
over time. So it's 500 jewels
/ 4 seconds.
500 / 4 is 125. So the lamp emits 125
watts of power. So that means in 1
second it transfers 125 jewels every
second.
So in 4 seconds it transfers or emits
500 jew of energy.
Now what about part B? What is the
intensity of the light source 1 meter
away from the lamp?
So we can use this equation
to find that answer.
So it's going to be the power which is
125 watts / 4 * 1^ 2.
So 125 / 4 pi
is 9.95
watts per square meter.
Now what about part C? What is the
intensity 2 and 3 meters away from the
lamp?
So let's draw a picture.
So let's say this is the light source
and we know at a distance of 1 meter
the intensity is about
9.95
watts per square meter.
So, how much is it 2 meters away?
And how much is it 3 m away? As you move
away from the light source, the
intensity decreases.
It's brighter when you're closer to the
lamp, but it appears dimmer or less
intense when you move away from the
lamp.
Now according to the inverse square law
if we double the distance
the intensity is going to be 1/4 of its
original value. So we can take 9.95 and
just divide it by four.
And so you should get an answer of about
2.49.
So that's the uh new intensity at a
distance of 2 m. Now, what about at a
distance of 3 m?
So, it's going to be 1 over 3^2, which
is 1 over 9. So, it's going to decrease
by a factor of 9. So, we need to divide
9.95 by 9. And you should get the answer
1.1
watts per square meter.
The intensity of the sun at a certain
location on Earth, let's say it's 12,200
watts per square meter, how much solar
power can be received on a rectangular
plot of land that is 30 m by 40 m.
So let's say if
here we have a rectangular plot of land
and
it's 30 m by 40 m
and let's say this is the sun
and it shines its
rays across this uh rectangular plot of
land.
So, how much solar power can be
received?
So, we're looking for the power in
watts.
How can we find the answer?
And we have the intensity. So, we know
that intensity
is power divided by area. In this case,
we don't need a surface area of a
sphere.
What we need is just the area of the
region that receives the solar light. In
this case, the area of a rectangle.
So power is intensity time area. If you
multiply both sides by a, you'll get
this equation.
So what is the area? The area is
basically length time width. 40 * 30. 4
* 3 is 12. So 40 * 30 is 1200.
You need to add the two zeros. So it's
1,200 square meters. The intensity is
1,200 watts per square meter. And if we
multiply that by 1200 m,
the unit square meters will cancel
giving us the power in watts.
So what is 1200 * 1200?
1200 squar is basically
It's uh a big number. It's 1,440,000
watts.
So that's how much power is being
received by this plot of land.
So now we can answer the next part.
How much energy in jewels can be
collected in a muff given a power of
1.44* 44
* 10 6 watt.
So if you recall power is energy divided
by time. So if we multiply both sides by
t we can see that the energy is power
multiplied by time. The power is
measured in watts or jewels per second.
So if we multiply by the unit seconds we
can get the energy in jewels.
So how many seconds are in a month?
Let's find out. So let's start with one
month. And we know that there's 30 days
in a single month.
And in a single day
there's 24 hours.
And in each hour there's 60 minutes. And
in a single minute there's 60 seconds.
So the unit months cancel, days cancel,
hours will cancel and minutes will
cancel. So it's going to be 30 * 24 * 60
* 60.
So there's 200 Well, it's actually
2,592,000
seconds in a month.
So now we can calculate the energy
collected.
So it's going to be 1.44 44 * 10 6 watt
which is really jewels per second
time
2.592*
10 6 seconds.
So as you can see the unit seconds will
cancel giving us the total energy in
jewels. So let's multiply these two
numbers.
So this is equal to 3.73
* 10 12
jewels.
So that's the total amount of energy
that will be collected in a month. By
the way, 10^ the 6 represents a million.
10^ the 9 represents a billion. 10^ the
12 represents a trillion. So you could
say it's about 3.73 trillion jewels will
be collected in this plot of land in a
single month.
The intensity of a light source is 48
watts per square meter at a distance of
30 cm from the source. What is the
intensity of the source at a distance of
15 cm?
So let's say S represents the source
at a distance of 30 cm.
The intensity is 48 watts per square
meter.
So if we move closer,
should the intensity go up or down?
So let's say if we're at 15 cm,
whenever you move closer to the source,
the intensity goes up. So it should be
higher than 48.
So we know that the intensity is
inversely related to the distance
squared.
So if we plug in 12,
1/2^ 2 is 1/4. 1 / 1/4 is 4. So it's
going to increase by a factor of 4. 48 *
is 192. So this is the answer.
But let's use the equation to get the
same answer.
So it's I2 / I1 which is equal to R1^ 2
/ R2 2. So we're looking for the second
intensity. The first one is 48.
The distance that corresponds to it is
uh 30 cm.
Now because we have a ratio we don't
need to convert our the centimeters into
meters. We can keep it in terms of
centimeters because those units will
cancel.
R2 is 15 cm.
So how can we solve it?
30^2
is 900
and 15 squared is 225.
900 / 225 is 4. So I2 is I2 / 48 is
equal to 4. So if we cross multiply I2 *
1 which is I2 is equal to 4 * 48
which we know it to be 192.
So it's 192 watts per square meter.
So what does this number mean? This
means that if you have a rectangle or
rather a square that is 1 meter by 1
meter, it's going to receive 192 Jew of
energy every second.
So this time we're dealing with
amplitude and distance.
So let's say this is the source
and at a distance of 2 cm
let's say this is 2 cm
the amplitude is 30.
What is the amplitude at a distance of
1 cm?
4 cm
and 6 cm.
So if you recall the amplitude is
inversely related
to the radius.
So if we double the distance, the
amplitude is going to be 1/2 of its
original value.
So at 4 cm it's going to be 15. And if
we triple the distance it's going to be
1/3 of its original value.
1/3 of 30 is 10. And if we cut the
distance in half
1 / 1/2 is four. I mean not four, two.
So it's going to be twice as large. So
if we move closer to the source, the
amplitude is going to double. It's going
to be 60.
Let's use the equation to find the
amplitude when it's 6 m away from the
source
relative to this point. So, we're going
to say A1 is 30 and we're looking for
A2.
R1, the distance that corresponds to A1
is 2 cm.
R2
is uh 6 cm.
So if we cross multiply 30 * 2 is 60
and that is equal to 6 * a2
60 / 6 is 10. So we get the same answer.
Now we're going to see how intensity is
related to amplitude and frequency.
Let's go over some equations.
Now we know that the period
of a spring is 2 pi * the square
of m / k.
And we also know that the mechanical
energy
is equal to 12 k * the square of the
amplitude.
So let's solve for k in this equation.
Let's do so by squaring both sides of
the equation.
t ^2 is equal to 4^2
* m / k.
Now let's multiply both sides by k.
So we have the expression kt t ^2 is
equal to 4^2 * m. And if we divide
both sides by t ^2, k is 4^2 m over
t ^2,
which I'm going to rewrite it like this.
Frequency is 1 / t.
So f2^2 is 1 over t ^2.
So therefore we can replace this
with f^2.
So now we can replace k with 4^ 2
m^2. So e is equal to 12 * 4^ 2 *
the mass * the square of the frequency
and the square of the amplitude.
Half of four is two. So the energy is
basically 2^ 2 * the mass * f^2 *
a^ 2.
Now our goal is to get the intensity in
terms of the area and the frequency.
So let's focus on m the mass.
Mass is density time volume because
density is mass / volume.
And if we draw let's say a rectangle
and let's say this is the
cross-sectional area. of the rectangle.
The volume of this rectangle
is the area of the cross-section, let's
call it S, times the length of the
rectangle.
So it's S * L.
So right now we have M is equal to P * S
* L. Now we know that d is equal to vt
and length and distance they share the
same unit which is meters. So we could
say l is equal to the velocity of the
wave multiplied by the time.
So m is equal to p s and we're going to
replace l with vt.
So we have the equation E is equal to
2i^2
density * the cross-sectional area time
the velocity * time F^2 * A 2.
Now we know that power is energy / time
and the energy is 2 pi^ 2 p sv
* t
times the square of the frequency and
the square of the amplitude. So we could
cancel the unit t or the variable t.
So now we have the equation
of the power of the wave. So now we
could find the intensity.
Intensity
is power divided by area. In this case,
the cross-sectional area is represented
by the letter S. So it's P / S. So
that's 2 2 P * S
V F^ 2 A 2 / S.
So the intensity of a wave is 2^ 2
time the density of the medium that the
wave travels through time the velocity
of the wave times the square of the
frequency and the square of the
amplitude.
So as we mentioned before the intensity
is proportional
to the square of the amplitude. We
talked about that earlier but also you
could see that the intensity is
proportional to the frequency.
So I2 / I1 is equal to A2 / A1 but
squared. You can also write a relation
between intensity and frequency. I2 I1
is equal to F_sub_2 / F_sub_1 but
squared as well.
Now the last thing that I'm going to
talk about in this video is the
principle of superposition. I won't
spend too much time uh talking about it,
but all you need to know is that waves
are additive. For example, let's say if
we have
a wave which has an amplitude of one
and another wave which has an amplitude
of two.
And notice that these two waves are in
phase with each other.
They both have a positive value at the
same time.
So if these two meet together they will
create a large wave with an amplitude of
three which is the sum total of the two
individual amplitudes.
So this is known as constructive
interference. Whenever two waves add and
if they add in such a way to increase
their amplitude you have constructive
interference.
Likewise
two waves can be out of phase.
Let's say if you have wave one which has
an amplitude of one
and wave two
but let's say it's out of phase with
wave 1
and let's say it's displacement is -2
when these two add 1 + -2 is negative 1.
So you're going to get a reduced wave.
That's an example of destructive
interference.
And if the two waves have equal
amplitudes but opposite in value,
then they will cancel out producing no
wave or a wave with a net amplitude of
zero, which is basically nothing.
So that's another example of destructive
interference.